Now the last topic in our series of best practices to manage project is professionalism.
والموضوع الأخير في سلسلة أفضل الممارسات لإدارة المشروع سيكون الاحترافية.
Professionalism is more of an attitude,
إن الاحترافية أكثر من مجرد موقف،
something that is displayed by the way you work with the clients.
وتظهر في طريقة تعاملك مع العملاء.
The way you take decisions,
وطريقة اتخاذك للقرارات،
the way you deal with unexpected situations.
وطريقة تعاملك مع المواقف غير المتوقعة.
In this part of the lesson,
في هذا الجزء من الدرس،
we'll talk about some areas of work in
سنتحدث عن بعض الجوانب في
your freelancing journey that could portray professionalism.
رحلة عملك الحر لإظهار الاحترافية المهنية.
But you'll realize that professionalism is something that is
لكنك ستدرك أن الاحترافية هي شيء
naturally developed as one works with clients all the time.
يتطور بتلقائية أثناء عملك مع العملاء.
First of all,
أولًا،
what I've learned in my freelancing career is that attention to
تعلمت في مهنة العمل الحر أن الاهتمام
detail goes a long way in making a successful freelancing career.
للتفاصيل هام جدًا في تحقيق النجاح في هذا المجال.
The client would love,
يُفضل العميل
if your work is detailed enough,
أن تهتم بالتفاصيل في عملك،
your communication is detailed and specific.
ويحب أن يكون تواصلك معه محدد ومُفصل.
If you're writing software code,
فإن كنت تكتب ترميز لبرنامج،
for example, the code is clear with comments.
فيجب مثلًا أن يكون الترميز مُوضح بتعليقات.
In fact, I would go on to say that do less if you have to but do it well,
في الواقع، أود أن أقول أن تعمل قليلًا ولكن بإتقان
instead of doing a bunch of things half-baked.
أفضل من أن تعمل الكثير بدون إتقان.
But you will realize that this aspect of attention
ولكنك ستدرك أن هذا الجانب الخاص بالاهتمام
to detail has to be balanced with pragmatism.
للتفاصيل يجب أن يتوازن مع الأسلوب العملي البرغماتي.
The client may be in a hurry to get the first version
فقد يكون العميل في عجلة من أمره ويريد الحصول على الإصدار الأول
out and may not want you to spend time on the details,
ولا يريد تضييع الوقت في التفاصيل،
in which case the scope of work is limited but
ففي هذه الحالة يكون نطاق العمل محدودًا ولكن
make sure you do a precise job within that scope.
تأكد من العمل بإتقان في إطار المشروع.
Try it out and see how it helps you in
جرب بنفسك لترى كيف سيساعدك ذلك في
your relationship with the client and future prospects.
علاقتك مع العميل وفي فرصك المستقبلية.
Knowing time and material projects precisely,
عندما تكون مُلم بالإطار الزمني والمادي،
logging time will not only give you satisfaction,
فتوفير الوقت سيجعلك راضي عن عملك،
but the client will appreciate our integrity to
وسيُقدر العميل نزاهتك في
precisely maintain a log of the time you spent.
توفير وقت العمل على المشروع.
You don't want to hurt your reputation for a few hours on the time log.
فأنت بالطبع لا تريد الإضرار بسمعتك من أجل كسب بعض ساعات العمل في سجب الوقت.
In some cases, I have even gone ahead and shared my precise time log with the client.
في بعض الحالات، قررت أن أتقاسم سجل وقتي الثمين مع العميل.
Even when I didn't have to and could just share with them the total spent,
حتى عندما لم أكن مضطرًا لذلك وكان يمكنني فقط مشاركة إجمالي الوقت،
but that gives more comfort and transparency to the client.
ولكن هذا يعطي المزيد من الراحة والشفافية مع العميل.
They feel more comfortable working with you.
ويشعر العميل براحة أكبر في العمل معك.
If you find yourself jacking up a few hours to gain some money,
إذا وجدت نفسك تحاول تمضية المزيد من ساعات العمل لكسب بعض المال
believe me, you're not the first one to try that,
صدقني، أنت لست أول من فعل ذلك،
but that'll only leave you dissatisfying.
وسيجعلك ذلك غير راضي عن نفسك.
There will always be an insecurity about the client questioning the time log,
سيكون هناك دائمًا حالة من عدم شعور العميل بالأمان،
leading to the lack of confidence in your work.
وسيشكك في سجل وقتك.
Lastly, attention to detail in
مما يؤدي إلى عدم الثقة في عملك
written and verbal communication not only portrays your professionalism,
وأخيرًا، فالاهتمام بالتفاصيل في
but it also gives an impression to
التواصل الكتابي والشفوي يحدد احترافيتك
the client that you're serious about what you're doing.
كما يعطي انطباع للعميل بجديتك في عملك.
Minor things like good grammar in an email,
أشياء بسيطة مثل الاهتمام بالقواعد النحوية في البريد الإلكتروني،
using correct cases in words,
واستخدام المفردات الصحيحة للكلمات،
naming convention of files,
وتسمية الملفات،
or perhaps variables in a source code.
أو المتغيرات في الترميز المصدر.
All of these do matter and demonstrate your alertness and seriousness towards the work.
كل هذه الأشياء مهمة وتُظهر اهتمامك وجديتك في العمل.
Next, being professional is good,
الأمر التالي: إن الاحترافية في العمل شيء جيد،
but being always professional is better.
ولكن الحفاظ على الاحترفية بشكل مستمر يكون أفضل.
I have discovered that being consistent in the quality of work,
لقد اكتشفت أن الثبات على الجودة،
the timelines, the deliverables,
وفي الالتزام بالجدول الزمني والأهداف أمر هام،
your consistent communication builds
فالثبات على الجودة يبني
clients' trust in you and this solid relationship with the client,
ثقة العملاء بك، وتنشأ علاقة قوية بينك وبين العميل،
could lead to a longer engagement and more projects in the future.
وسيؤدي ذلك إلى المزيد من الشراكة والعمل في المستقبل.
Next, as touched upon briefly in the previous lesson,
الأمر التالي وكما ورد بإيجاز في الدرس السابق،
it will demonstrate your professionalism if you
سيوضح هذا الأسلوب مهنيتك حيث
stay within the legal limits of any work that you do.
التزامك بالحدود القانونية في العمل.
For example, it's important to stay within the legal limits of the freelancing platform,
فعلى سبيل المثال، من مهم أن تلتزم بالحدود القانونية لمنصة العمل الحر
as we discussed earlier.
كما ناقشنا سابقًا.
If you bypass the platform and get the payment
إذا تجاوزت المنصة وحصلت على أموالك
directly from the client to avoid the intermediary fee,
بشكل مباشر من العميل لتتجنب رسوم الوساطة،
even if the client is happy with that,
فحتى إن كان العميل سعيد بذلك،
you may see losing their respect over time.
فقد تفقد احترامه لك.
If you're using third party libraries in your code,
إذا كنت تستخدم مكتبات جهة خارجية في التعليمات البرمجية،
for example, the GitHub library,
على سبيل المثال مكتبة GitHub،
it's important to check the licenses and
من المهم التحقق من التراخيص
discuss with the client it's applicability in their project.
ومناقشة العميل بخصوص قابلية تطبيق ذلك في مشروعه.
Lastly, doing things right,
وأخيرًا، فالالتزام بالأسلوب السليم،
give some authority which can only be understood with your own practical experience.
يُمدك بصلاحيات ستفهمها من خلال تجربتك العملية.
Now sometimes in your freelancing career,
الآن، في بعض الأحيان خلال حياتك المهنية الحرة،
things may not go as expected.
قد لا تسير الأمور كما هو متوقع.
The client may not echo to what was discussed at the outset.
قد لا يلتزم العميل بما اتفقتوا عليه في البداية.
The scope may change significantly or
وقد يتغير إطار العمل بشكل كبير أو
the client's deadlines will suddenly change expecting you to meet them.
يُغير العميل المهلة الزمنية بشكل مفاجئ ويتوفع منك الانتهاء في الموعد الجديد.
The culture in the client's organization may not be courteous enough
قد لا تكون الثقافة في مؤسسة العميل مهذبة بما فيه الكفاية،
even if you are trying to maximize value for the client and being professional.
حتى وإن حاولت الاهتمام بمصلحته أولًا والتزمت بالمهنية.
Now, this is the time to focus on ethical communication,
هذا هو الوقت المناسب للتركيز على التواصل الأخلاقي،
which could go really a long way instead of reacting
وسيكون ذلك أفضل من اتباع أسلوب رد الفعل،
to the situation which could lead to a long-term loss.
الذي قد يؤدي لخسائر على المدى الطويل.
Sometimes responding instead of reacting helps us a big deal.
أحيانًا يكون الفعل خير من اتباع أسلوب رد الفعل.